#現在我們煮點飯餵竹鼠哦
Now we're going to cook some rice for the bamboo rats.
#餵這個 竹鼠吃這個 吃這個米飯拌糠的 你看 (註︰他說開「米糠伴飯」的，但這樣說也沒差，不惡搞他了)
Feed them with, the bamboo rats, the rats need to be fed with this kind of rice with bran. Look!
#這些大米都是人都可以吃的
This rice is also edible for human.
#你看 很漂亮的哦
Look! It's pretty.
#都是在農戶 農戶手上收的這個大米
It's collected, collected directly from the farmers.
#他們今年 剛收割回來的
They've just harvested it this year.
#不過今年的大米好像又便宜了一點點
But it seems that the rice this year is getting a bit cheaper again.
#這裡七八斤 七八斤
Here is almost 4 kg, 4 kg,
#七八斤大米
almost 4 kg of rice.
#我洗一下
Wash it.
#這個是有營養的哦 這個米皮 (註︰其實米皮是甚麼？)
In fact the water becomes very nutritious, with the "mipi" (lit: skin of rice)
#可以啦 這個不用洗那麼久
Alright! It doesn't need to be washed too much.
#這個都是沒經過打蠟的
The rice has not been waxed.
#就是在農戶手上
From the farmers,
#直接收購那個穀 稻穀啊 收購我們自己去碾回來的
we bought the paddy, the paddy directly. We bought it and husked it ourselves.
#這個鍋是十升的
It's a 10 L cooker.
#餵竹鼠要兩鍋 現在煮好一鍋啦
We need two pots for the bamboo rats. Here's one.
#還有一鍋正在煮
The other is still being cooked.
#中午我們也是吃這個飯
In fact the rice is our lunch as well.
#吃了 吃了剩下的全部給竹鼠吃
We feed, feed ourselves first, and the rest is all for the bamboo rats.
#你看 現在已經攪拌均勻啦
Look! It's now well mixed.
#這個米糠跟米飯的比例啊
The bran to rice ratio,
#就這樣就
as you can see,
#看這樣就行啦
this is good enough.
#我一放的話 它這裡會散掉 你看
It's shattered when I'm not squeezing it. Look!
#這樣就是比較那個
So it's rather, I mean,
#水份在百份之六七十 七八十左右
the moisture is around 60 to 70 percent, 70 to 80 percent.
#七八十 不是六七十哦
I mean 70 to 80, not 60 to 70.
#七八十左右 這個水份
It's around 70 to 80 percent, the moisture.
#這樣就可以啦
And it's good enough.
#它這樣吃的話就不會黏 黏在口腔上 (註︰我不想用"Oral cavity"，太formal了)
It won't be sticking inside the mouth,
#或者你[SIC]黏在那個腸子裡面
or on the, the guts.
#秋天的話盡量拌濕一點
The moisture needs to be relatively higher in autumn.
#因為天氣比較乾燥 所以
As it's drier in autumn,
#吃的話水份也比較足
we need to let the rats take enough water.
#水份足的話就不會 不會那麼 太乾啦
So that they won't feel too, too dry,
#或者口渴啊 之類的
or too thirsty, or whatever.
#可以 等下我們抬過去
Alright! We'll take it to the barn.
#這個餵飯 餵那個米糖拌飯之前啊
Before giving the rice, I mean the rice with bran,
#要把這個 竹鼠屎掃一下
we need to clear, clear the poo from the cell first.
#不然等一下把這個糞便 糞便跟那個飯拌在一起 (註︰竟然突然說「糞便」，那我只好跟著吧)
Otherwise, the rice, the rice will get mixed with the feces.
#等下它又
And the rats will,
#把那個糞便都吃掉了
eat the feces with the rice.
#這個竹鼠很笨的
The bamboo rats are stupid.
#吃飯啦 吃飯啦
Meal time, meal time!
#好好吃的哦
It's really tasty.
#一人一勺啊
Everybody gets a spoonful.
#不要搶哦
No scrambling!
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#攝影小哥他媽媽喊他回家吃飯啦
Mr. Cameraman's mom is calling him back home for dinner.
#要趕回去
He's gotta leave now.